You could get sued for that.
这样做你可能会被起诉
TOKYO DISTRICT COURT
（东京地方法院）
Sorry to keep you waiting.
让你久等了
Nice to meet you.
幸会
Are you Mr. Haneoka? I'm the paralegal--
你是羽根冈律师？我是律师助理…
Ms. Shoko Ishida. I know.
石田硝子小姐 我知道
Thank you for taking on this case. My father strained his back--
谢谢你临时接下这次的案件 我爸闪到腰…
I know that too.
这我也知道
Do you always waste time?
你一直都这么浪费时间吗？
I've read the materials. Let's hurry.
资料我已经看过了 我们走吧
However, as a premise,
不过 作为前提
she has no reason for a divorce and wants to avoid divorce proceedings.
女方没有离婚的理由 也想要避免离婚诉讼
Do you still not get it?
你还不懂吗？
They agreed to share the chores equally because they're both working.
因为两人都在工作 因此约定好要公平分担家务
But when they had a fight, even though it was her duty,
但是在两人吵架时 即使是她负责洗衣服
she intentionally excluded the husband's laundry.
她也会刻意排除老公的衣物
I believe this is a default of an obligation.
我方认为这违反了义务
She also banned him from smoking, a habit of his since before marriage.
此外老公在婚前就有抽烟的习惯 她却无条件禁止
And her unilateral decision to limit his beer consumption to one 350 ml can
啤酒也是 她单方面决定 一次只能喝一罐350毫升的
were acts of moral harassment that caused unbearable stress to my client.
这都对我的委托人造成了压力 已经构成了精神骚扰
In addition, she gave her husband only 400 yen for lunch,
此外 她只给先生400日圆午餐钱
when she enjoyed course lunches herself.
自己去跑去享受套餐
Such outrageous action has caused him financial and emotional stress--
这样的暴行 已经造成金钱和精神上的压力
No. Um…
不 那个…
My wife can be sweet, too.
我妻子也是有温柔的地方
Good work.
辛苦了
Are you sure that went well?
这样子好吗？
The client is only seeking an amicable divorce. But you--
委托人想要的是圆满离婚 你却…
By properly instilling the wife's wrongdoings
只要好好灌输妻子的恶劣行为
we're making the mediation committee stand on the husband's side.
调停委员会就会站在先生这一边
May I say something?
我可以说句话吗？
You may be a good lawyer,
你或许是很优秀的律师
but in terms of lawyer ethics, I felt that you made very dangerous statements.
但就律师伦理来说 可能会说出很危险的话
You could get sued by your client.
这样很可能会被委托人起诉
I doubt we'll ever meet again, but in the future--
我想我们不会再见面了 但未来…
You're hard-headed, aren't you?
你真是死脑筋
Ms. Ishiko.
石子小姐
Excuse me?
你说什么？
Shoko Ishida. "Ishi" means "stone." So, stone-headed Ishiko. Understood?
像石头一样死脑筋的石田硝子 简称石子 懂了吗？
Sono contento.
“索诺坎藤托”
By the way, about your attitude.
对了 你刚刚说话的态度
Aren't you being rude to your future partner?
对未来的工作伙伴也太不礼貌了吧？
What?
什么？
I'm officially hired starting next week.
下星期开始 我就正式被录用了
Dad, please explain!
这是怎么回事 爸爸？
Your voice is hurting my back. Ouch.
听到你的声音 我的腰又痛起来了
I thought you hired him just for the day.
那个人不是只来帮忙一天吗？
Well, I'm getting old. I thought I should hire someone new.
我年纪也大了 想要再找个人进来
Someone like him?!
即使如此 为什么要找他那样的人？
But it's already been decided.
这件事已经决定了
He's on our website too.
网站也登载他的资料了
-Ow, ow. -What?
-痛… -什么？
LAWYER YOSHIO HANEOKA
（羽根冈佳男律师）
"Call me Haneo."
“Call me羽男”
"I want to be a free man, who can fly anywhere like a feather."
“想成为羽毛一般轻盈 自由飞翔的男人”
What's with him?
这个人有什么问题？
TOWN OF BIG PORTIONS KAMOGAYA
（爆食小镇 鸭谷）
THREE DAYS LATER
（三天后）
Alright.
很好
Okay.
好
USHIO
（潮）
Our motto is "Be an umbrella to protect those who live earnestly."
我们的理念是 “成为认真生活之人的保护伞”
Whatever the request may be,
不管是什么样的委托
there's an important…
都要认真…
Please take it easy.
所长 你不用太勉强
Oh, really?
这样吗？
Then I guess I will.
就听你的
BE AN UMBRELLA TO PROTECT THOSE WHO LIVE EARNESTLY.
（成为认真生活之人的保护伞）
It's more spacious than I thought.
比我想得还要宽敞
Sono contento.
“索诺坎藤托”
Oh, can I see the materials I returned the other day?
对了 我可以看一下 上次还你的资料吗？
Sure.
好
I thought I'd take a look from a different angle.
我想从别的角度审视一下
"A charismatic phrase."
“有魅力的说话方式
"Maybe I should mutter something in Italian."
突然说几句意大利话很不错”
This was in the file.
这夹在资料里
"Neglecting husband's laundry is default of obligation."
“不洗老公的衣服是违反义务
"Banning smoking is moral harassment." I found these too.
禁止抽烟是精神骚扰” 这些话也写在上面
You accidentally slipped these help notes and were desperate to get them back.
你不小心把这些提醒字条夹在资料里 所以才急着想拿回去
Am I wrong?
我说错了吗？
Could you be acting out the unconventional great lawyers
你该不会想扮演 连续剧或小说里会出现的
that we see on TV shows and novels?
那种打破常规的天才律师吧？
Reading my notes without permission is a breach of privacy.
未经允许偷看他人笔记是侵犯隐私权
It wasn't on purpose.
我又不是故意看的
-Even so-- -Hang on! It's still my turn.
-即使如此… -等一下 我还没讲完
What?
什么？
Now, I'm guessing that was on purpose too.
我想当时那招也是故意的吧
That?
那招？
That, when you appeared just in time.
等到时间快到了才现身的那一招
I knew something was weird.
我就觉得很奇怪
I looked away because you weren't there, but I heard a voice.
我往两边看都没看到人 但一听到声音
And the next thing I know, you were there.
转过来一看 你已经站在那里了
You showed up in such a short time.
能在这么短的时间里出现
Weren't you just hiding behind the pillar to appear at the right time?
代表你一直躲在柱子后面 等到适当时机才出现吧
Sorry to keep you waiting.
让你久等了
And…
还有…
that "sono contento" you keep saying.
你一直在说的“索诺坎藤托”
Apparently, it means "satisfied."
好像是“我很满意”的意思
But it doesn't make sense at all.
我对这句话完全没共鸣
Sono contento.
“索诺坎藤托”
I'm sorry, but it's just lame. It's no Sonokong.
不好意思 不可能 对这句话不可能有共鸣
Who cares? There are tons of lawyers today.
有什么关系？现在满大街都是律师
It's saturated. So we need to show people what kind of lawyer we are.
已经呈饱和状态 所以律师一定要有自己的特色
There's cosplay lawyers and idol lawyers. I just happen to be a genius lawyer.
角色扮演律师、偶像律师 我只是刚好选择了天才律师
-I see. -It's called branding.
-原来如此 -这是在建立品牌
I figured we'd get more requests that way.
只要表现得像天才律师 就能增加委托案件
I'm happy to receive more requests.
委托案件能增加 我很乐见
But your actions and words could get us in trouble.
但你的言行举止会让我们惹上麻烦
We're a small firm. One scandal could put us out of business.
我们只是一家小律所 只要发生丑闻 我们就得关门大吉
Please stop that behavior right now.
请立刻停止这样的行为
-No. -Stop it.
-不要 -不能这样
No.
才不要
Your fake talent will be exposed in no time.
假装出来的才能很快就会被识破
I don't want to hear that from a paralegal!
我才不要听律师助理说教
From you, who still can't be a lawyer.
尤其是当不上律师的你
It's not that I can't be a lawyer. I choose not to be one.
我不是当不上律师 是我不要当
Huh?
什么？
To be honest, I don't think my legal abilities are inferior to yours.
说实话 我的律师才能 应该不会输给你
Yeah, right. That's not true.
不好意思 不可能
That's so lame.
这是不可能的
As a paralegal, I will assist you perfectly.
身为律师助理 我会尽力辅助你
Oh?
这样吗？
Hello, this is Ushio Law Firm.
你好 这里是潮法律事务所
I would like to request Mr. Haneoka to look at my case.
我想要委托贵事务所的羽根冈律师
What?
什么？
See?
瞧见没？
Oh, right. I see.
这样啊…
So, you saw me on the website.
你在网站上看到我
Yes.
是
I will make sure you will be sono contento.
我一定会让你 Sono Contento
"Sono"?
“Sono”？
Please have a seat.
请坐
Here.
请用
-He saw the website. -Thanks.
-他看到了网站 -谢谢
And he thought I was the one.
他心想就是我了
And what is your request?
所以呢 你要委托的内容是什么？
The thing is…
这个嘛…
I was charging my phone in a café
我在咖啡厅里给手机充电
and I got sued for that.
就这样被告了
Okay, let me confirm.
那么…让我确认一下
Mr. Oba, you've been frequently going to Café de Sevon for the past month,
大庭先生 你过去一个月 频繁到塞文咖啡馆消费
where you stay from 7 to 9:30 p.m.
从晚上七点待到九点半
and used their outlet to charge your phone.
用他们的插头给你的手机充电
-I didn't use that much. -It's a bother.
-我又没有用多少电 -这样我很困扰
In response, the café manager suddenly
因此 咖啡厅店长
demanded one million yen for emotional distress
突然以赔偿电费和精神伤害为由
on top of the electricity bill.
要求你赔偿一百万日圆
Is that correct?
对不对？
If I ignore him, he said he'll… You know.
我不理他 结果他说…就那个
No, I don't know.
不 我不知道
-He'll file civil and criminal lawsuits. -Oh, civil…
-他会提出民事和刑事诉讼 -民事…
How can he sue me for something like this?
他怎么能因为这种事就告我？
This isn't America.
这里又不是美国
How often do you go to this café?
你多久去一次这家咖啡馆？
Almost every day.
几乎每天都去
That often?
这么频繁？
I only have Wednesdays off and I work the rest of the week.
我只有星期三放假 其他天都要工作
So I stop by every day after work to do some small tasks.
所以 每天下班之后 我都会去那里处理一些杂务
Why this café?
为什么选这家咖啡厅？
It's cozy.
因为很舒适
And you work at--
你的工作地点是…
Car Captain. A used car dealership!
汽车队长 是一间二手车行
Right. Okay.
好的
What do you think? A million yen is just too…
怎么样 一百万日圆也太…
Um, first of all,
首先
um, can you see me?
听我说 你看得到我吗？
First of all, this is a warning letter.
首先 这只是警告信
You haven't been sued.
你目前还没有被告
Oh.
哦
However, Article 245 of the Penal Code states that
不过 刑法第245条明文规定
"electricity is considered a property."
“电力应视为财物”
Using the outlet without permission is a theft--
未经允许使用插座是盗窃罪…
Th-Theft?
盗窃？
Also, if it becomes a criminal case, the police will question and arrest you--
此外 变成刑事案件的话 警方就会来询问甚至逮捕你
A-Arrest?!
逮…逮捕？
-Let's calm down for a moment. -I'll be arrested?
-先冷静一下吧 -我会被逮捕吗？
-I'm sorry. -Let's take a deep breath.
-抱歉 请坐下 -深呼吸 一起来
And breathe out.
呼气
-Good. -Thank you.
-很好 -谢谢
I'm really sorry for what I did.
做这样的事 我也觉得很抱歉
But can we somehow settle for 100,000 yen?
但有没有办法能以十万日圆和解呢？
Okay.
好
Well, a million yen is a rip-off.
一百万日圆的确像是在敲竹杠了
By the way, our initial consultation is free.
对了 首次咨询免费
The retainer fee is 100,000 yen plus a contingency fee. Is that alright?
聘用费是十万日圆 成功酬金另外算 这样可以吗？
Yes.
是
Then your signature here please.
请在这里签名
Why are you following me?
你为什么跟着我？
You could cause trouble for us.
不知道你会不会惹麻烦
Don't worry. This is an easy case.
不要担心 这个案件很简单
There are cases where small claims were made into criminal charges.
也有小额损失 后来变成刑事案件的例子
In 2008, a teenager was arrested for charging her phone at a train station.
2008年 一名高中女生在车站 给手机充了三分钱的电而遭到逮捕
In 2010, a man who pulled electricity from a shared outlet was sentenced for--
2010年 一名男子从公用插头 擅自接电 被判刑一年 予以缓刑
It'll be fine.
不会有问题的
He'll back off if a lawyer shows up.
看到律师出现 他就会收手了
We believe that this claim for damages is clearly an overcharge.
因为我们认为 这次损害赔偿的要求金额太高了
And?
所以呢？
Huh?
什么？
It's too complicated.
太复杂了 我听不懂
Well, as I said…
不 所以说…
You're saying you can't comply, right?
总之 你们就是 不接受我的主张 对吧？
It's not that we can't comply. Not everything…
不是我们不接受 而是这样…
He stays for hours every day and even charges his phone. It's annoying.
他每天一坐就是几小时 还给手机充电 谁不会生气？
Right.
对
Have you warned him several times?
你提醒过他很多次吗？
No.
没有
Then…
这样的话…
There's a written warning.
警告写得很清楚
PLEASE DO NOT CHARGE
（禁止充电）
That's not really…
贴在那里实在…
Are you saying I'm at fault?
你要说错在我吗？
No, I meant--
不 我是说…
It may not be much, but it becomes a pretty big damage if everyone does it.
虽然金额不高 每个人都这样做的话 也会是很大的损失
Do you know how stressful it is?
你知道这压力有多大吗？
It's a million yen for many reasons. Also as a warning to other customers.
这也是对其他客人的警告 诸多考量之后才求偿一百万日圆的
This is not negotiable.
这一点没得商量
Could you reduce the amount? It's clearly--
金额可以少一点吗？这实在是…
Then let's just let the police or the court handle it.
那就交给警方和法院吧
We're getting nowhere bickering here.
在这里吵半天也不会有结果的
Um…
啊…
What's wrong? You suddenly went quiet.
怎么了？你刚刚突然不讲话了
It's no good.
不行了
Huh?
什么？
That manager won't back down.
那个店长不会退缩的
And he seems to have financial trouble.
他好像有金钱上的困扰
What?
什么？
The prices of the drinks were raised by 50 yen
饮料的价钱比一年前涨了50日圆
and 130 yen for pizza toast in a year.
披萨土司甚至涨了130日圆
You went there often?
你常去这家店吗？
No, just once.
没有 只有一次
Come on, pretending to be a genius--
又来了 假装是天才…
Let's persuade our client. Okay?
我们去说服委托人吧
If he can't pay, we should give up on settling.
拿不出一百万的话 就只能放弃和解了
Excuse me?
什么？
I'm giving up.
我要放弃
You're giving up way too early.
你也太快放弃了
If we can't settle, there'll be no contingency fee.
和解破裂的话 就拿不到成功酬金了
You negotiate with the manager then.
那你自己去跟店长交涉
You know that paralegals can't negotiate legally, don't you?
律师助理不能进行法律交涉 这点你很清楚吧？
Besides, I believe my role is to stay behind the scene
而且我的角色只不过是幕后人员
and assist the lawyers to do a good job.
任务就是辅佐律师把工作做好
It's against my rule to ignore you and stand out.
站出来抢你的锋头违反我的原则
I don't care about your rule.
谁管你什么原则
Mr. Haneoka!
羽根冈律师
Huh?
什么？
What's his problem?
怎么回事？
Hey, Shoko. Shoko?
硝子…
Could you raise my allowance--
我的零用钱可以多…
No.
不可以
Okay.
好
This month is tight again.
这个月手头也很紧张
ENGAGEMENT LETTER
（委任契约）
CONTINGENCY FEE
（成功酬金）
Hey, Oba. Make sure to empty the trash.
大庭 记得倒垃圾
Yes.
好
CAR CAPTAIN NEWS
（汽车队长新闻）
Slow down. Wait for me.
慢一点 等等我
PUSH BUTTON TO WALK
（按钮式红绿灯）
CHANGES IN RESTAURANT PROFITS UPON INTRODUCING ACCESS TO POWER OUTLETS
（餐厅开放插座之后的收益变化）
CAFÉ DE SEVON PAYMENT PLAN
（塞文咖啡馆付款计划）
I saw the light.
我看到一丝曙光了
What?
什么？
Can you proceed with the settlement with this?
你可以用这个来谈和解吗？
What is this? Calm down.
什么？你冷静一点
Here.
给你
Come on, do it yourself.
才不要 你自己去做吧
Like I said, only a lawyer can handle this.
我说过 只有律师才能处理此事
Excuse me. Hello.
不好意思 打扰了
I'm not going to negotiate.
我不会谈和解的
Let me get to the point.
我就单刀直入地说了
I believe you're having financial trouble.
你资金周转困难吧？
This café is rented, correct?
这个店面是租的 对吧？
And you're behind on your rent.
而且 拖延交租
I went to see the landlord.
我去找过房东了
I asked if I could rent it when the property becomes vacant.
我问他有没有可以租的物业
And he complained that the current tenant is behind on rent.
他就跟我抱怨现在的房客拖延交租
So what if I am?
是的话又怎样？
Maybe as a last resort to delay the rent payment,
作为拖延交租的最后手段
did you tell the landlord you're getting a large amount of money from this?
你告诉房东接下来会有大笔进帐吧？
If you can consider resolving Mr. Oba's case peacefully,
如果你考虑和大庭先生和解
we may be able to help you.
我们或许可以帮你
Such as negotiating to pay in installments.
协调分期偿还租金事宜
That's what you suggest. To terminate a lease agreement for…
向他提出这个建议 没有支付租金造成的
…not paying the rent, the court has established
租赁契约解约 法院已经认定
a standard that non-payment of rent isn't enough.
这不只是拖延交租这么简单
But there also must be a breach of trust between the landlord and the tenant.
房东与房客之间的信任关系 也会遭到破坏
Therefore…
因此
…it's important to first express clearly that
现在最重要的是要清楚表明
you're willing to pay and maintain a trusted relationship.
你愿意付款以维持信赖关系
When negotiating, it helps to have a payment plan…
进行交涉时 每个月的还款金额
…including the amount of monthly payment…
以及全数还清的时间表
…and the period of time…
拟定还款计划
…until the full payment is made.
交涉就能顺利进行
We have it here…
为以防万一
…just in case.
我们先准备了
If you would reconsider your claim against Mr. Oba…
如果愿意考虑跟大庭先生和解
…we'll help you with everything we have. What do you say?
我们会尽全力帮你去谈 你意下如何？
I'd love to get your help.
可以麻烦你们吗？
I panicked after he came in yelling at me for falling behind on rent once.
我才拖延一次就被房东骂死了 因此才惊慌了起来
That's why I ended up doing this.
不知道该怎么做 才会出此下策
I'm really sorry.
真的很抱歉
Oh, could you tell him I apologized?
可以帮我跟他道歉吗？
Please tell him in person.
你可以亲自告诉他
Huh?
什么？
I'm sorry for the trouble.
造成困扰 真的很抱歉
No, no. Me too.
不 我才是
Can I come to the café again?
我可以再来店里吗？
Yeah, of course. Come by anytime.
当然…随时欢迎
Thank you.
谢谢
Would you like a drink now?
你现在要喝杯咖啡吗？
I can't today, but thank you.
今天就不用了 但还是谢谢你
Thank you very much.
非常感谢
Thank you for the phone call.
感谢你的来电
Not at all. Thank you.
不会…谢谢你
I'm Sawamura.
我姓泽村
Thank you very much for everything.
真的很感谢你
I'm glad I could help.
很高兴能帮上忙
You too, Ishiko.
石子小姐 也谢谢你
Oh, I just work behind the scenes.
不 我只是幕后人员
Ishiko?
石子？
Huh? Oh.
什么？
Actually, I'm your junior from Nishi High School.
其实我是你西高的学弟
I was in the sports festival committee with you.
我跟你一起当过运动会执行委员
Oh, you're two grades below me.
你小我两届
Yes.
对
Isn't that cool? Seriously.
太厉害了吧 说真的
Hey!
嘿
I'm sorry. It's just, you seem quite different now.
不好意思 你整个人感觉都不一样了
No worries.
没关系
Ishiko?
石子？
That was her nickname back then because she's a hard worker. Right?
她以前的绰号 因为她总是很努力 不是吗？
Apparently, also because I'm hard-headed.
也有脑筋不会转弯的意思
So it's always been your nickname.
以前就有人这样叫你
I've always admired you.
我一向很崇拜石子小姐
Oh, no. I mean, you know…
不是 我是说…
You were smart and popular. I looked up to you.
因为你人聪明 又受欢迎 所以很景仰你
You wanted to be a lawyer back then, right?
你那时候是想当律师的 对吧？
I remembered that.
我想起这件事
But when I checked the firm's website, I only found Mr. Haneoka.
去查了你们事务所的网站 只看到羽根冈律师
That's why you chose me?
所以你才找我？
I'm sorry.
不好意思
It's fine.
不会
Aren't you going to be a lawyer?
你不当律师了吗？
Um, I'm not sure.
要怎么说呢？
Well, my train is here. Bye.
我的电车来了 再见
You're hiding something, aren't you?
你有事瞒着我们吧？
From your workplace,
大庭先生 从你的职场
Car Captain's workshop, your house and the café
也就是汽车队长维修厂 要回你家和前往咖啡厅
are in opposite directions.
是反方向
That means you've been going to a café all the way on the other side of town
也就是说你每天大老远 跑到跟回家方向相反的咖啡厅
just because it's cozy.
只是因为它很舒适
Also, there's a Car Captain branch across that café.
而且汽车队长的分店就在咖啡厅对面
And your usual seat has its perfect view.
从你常坐的位子看过去很清楚
I doubt this is a coincidence.
我想这并非巧合
Door's closing.
电车门要关了
There's something else you actually want to request, right?
你真正想委托的是其他事 不是吗？
Again.
又来了
I'm back.
我们回来了
Oh, they're back.
他们回来了
Hey, daughter.
嘿 女儿
Yup, the daughter’s here. Hello. Welcome.
对 我是女儿 你们好 欢迎
We're back.
我们回来了
Hi.
嗨
Wh-Who are those people?
这…这些人是谁？
Huh? They're my friends. Yeah.
我的朋友
Another party? Your back is not healed yet.
又开派对？你的腰还没好呢
Food tastes better if we all eat together, right?
大家一起享用 食物才会好吃 不是吗？
Oh, let me.
让我来吧
Really? Thanks.
是吗？谢谢
There.
好了
Did you reach a settlement?
和解还顺利吗？
Yes, successfully.
是 很顺利
Let's eat together.
一起吃饭吧
Oh, yes. Thank you.
好 不好意思
Isn't it great, Shoko?
硝子 这样不是很好吗？
But Mr. Oba still seems troubled about something else.
不过大庭先生好像还有烦恼
He wouldn't tell us what it is.
但他没有告诉我们
I see. A lot of Japanese people
明白了 大多数日本人
think that confiding in a lawyer is a last resort.
都把找律师当成最后手段
That American system, where people easily sue others,
像美国那种动不动就告人的体制
has a lot to do with their gun society,
虽然跟枪支社会有很大关系
but it prevents directly fighting each other and ruining relationships.
不过这也避免了个人冲突 演变成关系的破裂
Well, I guess we approach law in a completely different way.
我们面对法律的态度完全不一样呢
Yes, that's true.
的确如此
Yeah. Oh, is there a new ketchup?
对了 有新的番茄酱吗？
Wait! The one we have is still good.
等一下 这里还有剩下的
But that's…
但是那个…
See, there's so much left.
你看 还剩这么多
Geez, what a cheapskate.
老天 太小气了
Business is tough, you see.
经营困难 你懂的
-Oh, I'm sorry. -Sorry.
-不好意思 -抱歉
It's your fault, Dad. You keep consulting clients for free.
都是你的错 爸爸 一直免费提供咨询
If there's someone soaked in the rain, you'd hold an umbrella over them, right?
如果有人在雨里淋得湿漉漉的 任何人都会想要帮他撑伞吧
There you go again.
又来了
Shall we set a trap?
要来设陷阱吗？
DAY OFF
（假日）
As I thought, he's filming them.
他果然在偷拍
Go.
去吧
Okay, drop your pen.
把笔丢到地上
Drop it.
快丢
There.
是
Okay.
好
Bend over and pick it up with your back to the camera.
背对相机 弯腰把笔捡起来
Come on, bend over.
快点弯下去
What are you doing? He'll be suspicious.
你在做什么？他会起疑的
Get over here. We need to talk.
集合 我有话跟你说
I'm not doing this.
无法继续进行
-Get over here! -Don't shout.
-集合 -不要大喊大叫
Hurry.
快点
What is it?
是怎样？
This plan is useless now.
现在这个计划不能用了
It was useless to begin with.
从一开始就不能用了
What?
怎么了？
You want Mr. Oba to film my backside and use that against him.
你想让大庭先生拍下我的不堪画面 再借此质问他吧
Yup.
对
And we can ask him what he's doing.
让他无法回避 问他到底想做什么
This is sexual harassment against me.
这是对我的性骚扰
What are you thinking in this day and age?
都什么年代了 你到底在想什么？
Rude.
真没礼貌
And this deceitful conduct to have such a moment filmed
而且自己引诱对方拍摄那一瞬间
and using that on him is against my rules.
再借此要挟对方的诈骗行为 违反我的原则
This is to get us a case. We need the money, right?
这是要让对方委托我们 我们不是经营困难吗？
Still!
不行！
If he finds out what we're doing, we could get sued instead.
这种行为要是被他发现 我们反而会被告吧？
Don't be such a stiff. It's a gray area.
别那么顽固 只要游走在灰色地带边缘不就好了
What? Don't be silly.
什么？别犯傻
What are you doing here?
你们在这里做什么？
Are you spying on me?
你们在监视我吗？
No.
没有
You said something about getting sued, right?
你们刚刚说了会被告什么的 对吧？
Can I get sued for what I'm filming?
我录像的话会被告吗？
I really am in trouble. Aren't I?
我果然做了不好的事吗？
That's right.
没错
We were so worried when we found out that you're secretly filming them, right?
我们就是知道你在偷拍 很担心你才会这样做 对吧？
Yes.
对
I wasn't sure if I should ask for help.
我很犹豫要不要找你们商量
Right.
是
Let me confirm.
让我确认一下
You used to work at the Car Captain Koide branch
你以前在赛文咖啡馆对面的
across the street from Café de Sevon.
汽车队长小井手分店工作
But the branch manager Yano puts pressure on the employees to increase the sales
但矢野分店长为了跟其他分店竞争
in order to compete with other branches.
强迫员工要提升业绩
At times, it went beyond power harassment to what we call workplace bullying.
有时会做出超越职场骚扰 堪称职场霸凌的行为
That's right.
没错
The bullying was especially harsh towards you.
尤其对你的霸凌特别严重
You were taunted for being inefficient and unsociable
骂你做事不得要领 不讨人喜欢
and were reprimanded for hours every day.
每天长时间斥责你
He either gave you no work at all
不是不给你工作
or forced a huge amount of work on you.
就是给你加大工作量
On top of that, he told everyone in the sales department to ignore you.
甚至叫业务部的同事忽视你
They took part so they wouldn't be his target
他们怕自己也成为目标
and treated you like you didn't exist.
开始把你当成隐形人
That's right.
没错
The only one who treated you well was your colleague, Atsuhiko Sawamura.
唯一还会跟你互动的 是同期的泽村笃彦先生
But one day, after helping you
但有一天 他看到你
with the huge amount of work you were forced to do,
被指派了大量工作 他看不下去而出手相助
Mr. Sawamura also became a target of bullying.
结果泽村先生也成了职场霸凌的对象
That's too much work for one person.
这么多 一个人做不完的
Thanks. Sorry.
谢谢 不好意思
In the sales group chat,
业务部的群组信息
you get scolded unless you reply within two minutes after the message is read.
没在已读后两分钟内回复会被责骂
And messages are sent regardless of it being a late night or an early morning.
而且不管深夜或清晨 都照发信息
If you don't respond, you'll be reprimanded again.
没有回复一样会被骂
From all the pressure, Mr. Sawamura had a nervous breakdown
承受这么大的压力 泽村先生精神崩溃
and began to make more trivial mistakes.
开始犯下一些微小的错误
One day, the branch manager
有一天 分店长以此为理由
hit him over that mistake.
殴打了泽村先生
Yes, I'm so sorry.
是 非常抱歉
That's right.
没错
You reported the branch manager's conduct to the company.
目击此事的你 向公司告发分店长的行为
However, the head office only interviewed the branch manager and determined that
然而总公司没有听泽村先生的说法 只凭分店长的片面之词
there was no evidence of bullying.
就判断没有职场霸凌
Right after that, you were transferred to the workshop.
在那之后 你就被调到维修厂
That's where you work now. Correct?
就是你现在工作的地方？
Yes.
对
I think it's because of the accusation I made.
我想是因为我去告发的关系
Sawamura…
泽村…
is probably…
现在大概…
still getting bullied.
还在一直被霸凌
Even if I told him to leave evidence,
即使我叫他要留下证据
he'd be too afraid of retaliation.
他也会怕遭到报复而不敢吧
So I thought I would.
我就想让我来吧
I filmed them every night.
每晚用手机录像
But even after a month, I couldn't get anything.
但是盯了一个月 还是一无所获
Um…
这件事…
I'm sorry I didn't tell you.
没有告诉你们 对不起
Mr. Oba.
大庭先生
Bullying should be brought to justice by law.
霸凌应该要受到法律制裁
Words like "idiot" and "go to hell" are insults.
“笨蛋”、“去死” 这种骂人的话构成侮辱罪
Spreading baseless rumors is defamation.
散播没有根据的谣言构成毁谤罪
Forcing you to do something is extortion.
强迫他人做事构成强制罪
Hitting someone is assault.
殴打他人是伤害罪
Without a doubt.
这些都是犯罪
Please help me.
请帮帮我
I want to save Sawamura somehow.
无论如何 我都想要救泽村
Leave it to us.
交给我们
-Sorry. -That was on purpose.
-抱歉 -你是故意的吧
ARTICLE 230 OF THE PENAL CODE DEFAMATION
（刑法第230条 诽谤罪）
-Good work, sir. -You too.
-你辛苦了 -辛苦了
ARTICLE 208 OF THE PENAL CODE ASSAULT
（刑法第208条 伤害罪）
Sawamura.
泽村
Why are you…
你为什么…
Did you lose weight again?
你又瘦了？
Oh, excuse me.
不好意思
I'm Haneoka, a lawyer.
我姓羽根冈 是一名律师
About the bullying in--
关于职场霸凌的事情…
I have nothing to say.
我无可奉告
W-Wait. Don't worry. They're on your--
等…等一下 别担心 他们是站在你…
Excuse me.
我先走了
He's probably afraid of the company finding out.
他一定是怕公司的人发现吧
Thanks for everything. The landlord agreed to wait for the rent.
这一切都要谢谢你们 房东同意让我缓交租金
And this.
还有这个
Thanks to you, we're now busy.
多亏了你们 现在生意忙起来了
I guess everyone was looking for a place to charge.
大家都想要找地方充电
May I?
我也可以吗？
Of course.
请用
-Excuse me. -Coming.
-不好意思 -来了
Enjoy.
请慢用
Thank you.
谢谢
-Good morning.
-早安
Our fifth-anniversary sale starts tomorrow.
明天起是我们的五周年纪念特卖会
-Please stop by. -Thank you.
-欢迎来看看 -谢谢
A FEW HOURS AGO
（几小时前）
"Fifth-anniversary sale"?
“五周年纪念大特卖”？
Yes. I was suddenly asked to go to the Koide branch tomorrow.
对 他们突然叫我明天 去小井手分店支援
They're short-staffed and need help.
说是人手不足 需要帮忙
Apparently, the branch manager requested it.
好像是分店长要求的
This is our chance.
这是我们的机会
I wonder what'll happen tomorrow.
不知道明天会发生什么事
You think we'll get any proof?
有办法取得证据吗？
What?
怎么了？
Huh?
什么？
Oh, my, my.
天哪
Be careful. You spilled it.
小心点 都洒出来了
-Is this… -A month's worth of Mr. Oba's recording.
-这是… -大庭先生拍的一个月份视频
I was looking for a proof.
我在想会不会拍到什么证据
That's so unexpected.
好意外
You do this kind of dull work too?
你也会做这么无聊的工作？
What do you think I am? You won't find an earnest lawyer like me anywhere.
你把我当成什么了？ 找不到比我还认真的律师了
Really?
是吗？
Excuse me. We're from Car Captain.
不好意思 我们是汽车队长的员工
Okay.
是
We saw you talking to Sawamura last night.
昨晚我们看到你们跟泽村讲话
I understand you're a lawyer, but I think you're mistaken.
听说你们是律师 但我想你们是不是有什么误会
It wasn't the branch manager who harassed Sawamura.
职场骚扰泽村的人不是分店长
It was Oba.
而是大庭
-Excuse me? -What?
-你说什么？ -怎么会？
He was transferred because of power harassment.
他就是因为职权骚扰才被调职的
Oba always said harsh things to Sawamura.
大庭对泽村讲话总是非常严厉
Messages like these were daily occurrences.
发这种信息是家常便饭
May I?
借我看一下
YOU DONE YET? CALL ME.
（还没做完吗？打电话给我）
He was pressuring and rushing him.
这些催促的话感觉就像在施压一样
I can understand feeling pressured by this.
这样看感觉确实有点压力啦
But transferring him for this--
不过因此就把他调职有点…
This is the worst one.
最过分的是这个
After this, he couldn't deny his actions and he was transferred.
他之后无法否认自己的所作所为 因此才被调职的
ENOUGH ALREADY
（你给我差不多一点）
HOW MANY TIMES NOW? JUST QUIT ALREADY
（已经多少次了 干脆辞职算了）
It's not a screenshot, so it's not fake.
这不是屏幕截图 所以不是伪造的
JUST DIE
（去死吧）
What do you think?
你们觉得呢？
Can I have your business cards first?
可以跟你们要张名片吗？
-Of course. I'm sorry. -Sorry.
-当然 不好意思 -不好意思
Is Mr. Oba here?
请问大庭先生在吗？
He's not here today.
他今天没来
I see. Thank you.
我知道了 谢谢
Please help me.
请帮帮我
I want to save Sawamura somehow.
无论如何 我都要救泽村
This is Oba. I can't answer the phone right now…
我是大庭 现在不方便接听…
Mr. Oba is absent.
大庭先生没去上班
Mr. Sawamura back then.
那个时候泽村先生
He also seemed to be afraid of Mr. Oba.
看起来很怕大庭先生
He could be resenting them for the transfer and plotting revenge.
他可能因为调职而怀恨在心 想要报复啊
What?
什么？
I can't.
不行了
Let's turn down this case.
把这个案子推掉吧
But we've already accepted--
但是我们已经接案…
He hid things from us once.
他先前就对我们有所隐瞒了
This is too risky. It'll ruin my brand.
这样太冒险了 会坏了我的品牌
Your brand?
品牌？
Do it on your own.
要做你自己去做
Like I said, a paralegal can't do this on my--
我已经说了 律师助理没办法自己去…
Then just give up. Since you are a paralegal.
那就放弃 反正你只是律师助理
Fine. I'll give up.
好 我会放弃
I'll give up expecting anything from you.
放弃对你的期待
Slowly lower your center of gravity.
慢慢把重心放低
Right hand, up. Left hand, down.
举起右手 放下左手
Like you're holding a ball, bring in your left leg.
像抱球一样 靠近你的左脚
-You okay? -I'm fine.
-你还好吗？ -我没事
Don't strain yourself.
不要太勉强了
I can invoice tabs that are up to five years old?
五年前赊的帐还能去讨吗？
That's right.
可以
That's great news.
太好了
A lot of my customers have open tabs.
我们店里好多人赊账 我正在头疼呢
-Oh, really? -Yes.
-是吗？ -对
Shoko will get mad again if I ask for your advice like this.
找你咨询这种事 硝子知道一定又会生气吧
What's that?
这是什么？
-Is there a point? -Yes.
-有意义吗？ -有啊
Rock, paper, scissors!
石头、剪刀、布
Yes!
太好了！
You're so bad at this.
你真的很不会猜拳
-So bad. -Hush.
-太逊了 -闭嘴
Drink whatever you want.
随便你想喝什么
How long have you been living together?
你们一起住多久了？
About three years.
大概三年
But she's still polite.
但她还是对你讲敬语
Big emotional distance.
很有距离感吧
That's what I love about her, Dad.
她就是这一点好 爸爸
Don't call me dad.
不要叫我爸爸
-I got a haircut. -So?
-我剪头发了 -所以呢？
Will she notice it?
她会注意到吗？
I've no idea.
我不知道
Come on.
拜托
-Dad. -Geez.
-爸爸 -哎呀
Excuse me, I need to talk to you.
不好意思 我有事要跟你讨论
Oh, hello.
你好
Good evening.
晚上好
Hey, do I seem different today?
我今天看起来有什么不一样吗？
Huh?
什么？
-I don't know. -See?
-不知道 -瞧见没？
I can't tell. I've never looked at you that closely.
看不出来 我从来没有仔细看过你
You okay? Stay strong.
你还好吧？振作一点
There's always tomorrow.
明天一定会更好
-Hang in there. -Okay.
-加油 -好
What do you need?
你要跟我谈什么？
Oh.
哦
Could you replace him?
可以把他换掉吗？
What?
什么？
Mr. Haneoka and I have very different rules.
羽根冈律师跟我的原则完全不一样
I don't know
我不知道
if I can work with him from now on.
接下来该怎么跟他合作
This is where I first met him.
我跟他第一次相遇就是在这里
He was having trouble with pool tickets.
他在游泳池的售票机前面犹豫了好久
So I recommended him to buy a set of tickets if he comes often.
我就推荐他如果常来的话可以买套票
What a strange encounter.
这是什么奇怪的邂逅
That was all that day.
那天就只有这样
I saw him again three weeks later in a Tai Chi class.
再次遇见他是三周后的太极拳教室
So he does Tai Chi.
他也会打太极拳
He thanked me for the other day, but I didn't remember.
他谢谢我前些日子的帮忙 但我完全不记得了
I asked him how he knew it was me, when I was wearing sunglasses and a hat.
当时我戴了墨镜和帽子 我问他是怎么认出我的？
And he said he knew from the shape of my ears.
他说是从耳朵形状看出来的
Ears?
耳朵？
Incredible, right?
不可思议 对吧？
Apparently, he memorizes everything instantly.
很显然 他有过目不忘的能力
-Sir. -Hi.
-律师 -你好
I got curious, so I had a chat with him.
我很好奇 就跟他聊了一下
And I found out that he's a lawyer, who passed the preliminary and bar exam
这时才知道他虽然只是高中毕业 但司法预试和律师资格考试
in one try despite being a high school graduate.
都是一次就考过 当上了律师
Me too.
我也是
You're a lawyer?
你也是律师？
Yes.
我是律师
Really?
这样啊？
In one try?
一次就考过了？
But he couldn't accommodate the clients' request in every case he took on.
但他接下来的案件 都无法达成委托人的期望
So he was fired and was looking for a job.
他就被律所开除了 正在找工作
Even though he's so smart?
他这么聪明的人都不行吗？
The thing is…
问题是…
Thank you.
谢谢
Have you heard of photographic memory?
你听说过影像记忆吗？
No. What is it?
没有 那是什么？
It's an ability to memorize everything like a photograph.
能像照片一样把东西都记下来的能力
I see.
这样啊
I passed only because I have a good memory.
所以我考上只是因为记忆力很好而已
But…
可是…
With such great ability, no lawsuit is difficult--
有这样的能力 碰到什么案件都不会有问题吧
Well, this job is not just memorizing articles and precedents, right?
这份工作不只是 需要记住条文和判例而已吧
That's true.
没错
The important thing is to apply my knowledge to the situation.
重要的是要把知识应用到实际情况中
But I can't deal with unexpected events.
但我应付不来出乎意料的案件
If my prepared plan fails, I don't know how to overcome it
如果准备好的计划失败了 就会不知道要如何处理
and I freeze up on the spot.
当场僵在那里
Is there a reason for that?
这其中有什么原因吗？
Well…
这个嘛…
The price of the drinks were raised by 50 yen
饮料的价钱比一年前涨了50日圆
and 130 yen for pizza toast in a year.
披萨土司甚至涨了130日圆
He's suffering too.
他也很痛苦吧
Then let's just let the police or the court handle it.
那就交给警方和法院吧
We're getting nowhere bickering here.
在这里吵半天也不会有结果的
I think I said too much again.
我好像又多嘴了
Welcome.
欢迎光临
Sorry to barge in.
抱歉这样突然跑来
Sorry about tod--
今天很抱…
Those messages to Mr. Sawamura…
泽村先生收到的职权骚扰信息
Did you really send them?
真是你发的吗？
Yes.
是的
Please come in.
请进
So you were secretly filming the branch to get back at them for the transfer?
所以你偷拍分店是因为调职而不满 想要进行报复吗？
Then what exactly did you want to do when you asked for my help?
这样你还来委托我 你到底想干什么？
Welcome.
欢迎光临
Car Captain…
汽车队长…
Here, have a balloon. It's a hippo.
来 气球给你 是河马
Here you go.
请拿好
Sure. Please follow me.
好 这边请
Thank you.
谢谢
Car…
汽车…
Yes, what is it?
是 怎么了？
Uh…
嗯…
You're not coming in today?
你今天不进办公室吗？
No. We have no case, right?
我们没有案子 对吧？
Then at least let me know.
那至少要跟我说一声
Okay, I'm sorry.
是 抱歉
Car Captain
汽车队长
Are you outside?
你在外面吗？
Well, yeah.
是 有点事
I can hear the "Car Captain" jingle.
我听到了“汽车队长…”的口号
I think you're hearing things.
你听错了吧
No, I can hear it clearly.
不 我听得很清楚
Are you at the Koide branch?
你人在小井手分店吗？
You said you turned down the case because he admitted to harassment.
你说他承认职权骚扰 所以推掉了他的委托吧？
Um, this is my private time. Bye.
现在是我的私人时间 再见
What? Wait a minute.
什么？等一下
What's going on?
怎么回事？
Come on…
快点…
-You scared me. -Why are you here?
-吓死我了 -你来做什么啦？
What are you plotting?
你在打什么主意？
Nothing! I told you, it's my private time.
哪有打什么主意 我已经说了 现在是我的私人时间
Actually…
其实…
I'm keeping an eye on him.
我在监视他啦
Mr. Oba might do something to Mr. Sawamura as retaliation.
不知道大庭先生会不会为了报复 对泽村先生做出什么事
Um, could you take over my client?
可以请你接手我这一组客人吗？
-Though you declined? -My hands are full.
-即使你推掉了他的委托？ -我已经忙不过来了
I don't mind.
可以
All you need is their signature.
接下来只要请他们签名就好
I'll be taking over from here.
接下来由我为你服务
You're in my way.
你挡到我了
I'm Oba.
敝姓大庭
What kind of car are you…
你想要找什么样的车…
Please follow me.
那么 请跟我来
Thank you for waiting.
久等了
Thank you very much.
谢谢光临
Nothing happened, huh?
什么事都没发生 对吧？
Yeah.
对
Oba.
大庭
Yes.
是
You messed up, Oba.
你闯祸了 大庭
You sold the car with reduced mileage. You tampered with the meter, huh?
你卖车时少报了里程数 里程表动过手脚了 对吧？
What's this about?
这是怎么一回事？
This is the car you sold, right?
这辆车是你签约的 对吧？
Did you do this to increase sales?
这么做是为了提升业绩吗？
No. I didn't do anything.
不 我什么也没做
You're the one who was in charge.
负责签约的人是你吧？
I just…
我只是…
I took over Sawamura's client.
接手泽村的客人而已
Is that true, Sawamura?
是这样吗 泽村？
I know nothing about that.
我什么都不知道
Oba, you really shouldn't lie.
大庭 说谎就不对了
I didn't do this.
真的不是我做的
Fine. I got it.
算了 我知道了
Please listen.
请等一下
Let's talk in the office.
我们到办公室里面谈
Let's go.
走吧
Hey.
等一下
Let me go.
不要拉我
Don't make a scene.
别让场面变难看了
It's not me.
真的不是我
Stop causing trouble for your colleagues…
不要造成同事的困扰…
I'm sorry, but we're--
不好意思 我们已经…
Excuse me.
打扰了
I will be taking over from here.
接下来由我接手处理
I'm sorry, but who are you?
不好意思 请问你哪位？
I'm Yoshio Haneoka. A lawyer representing Mr. Oba.
我是代表大庭先生的律师 羽根冈佳男
A lawyer?
律师？
And she is…
这位是…
I'm Shoko Ishida. A paralegal.
我是律师助理石田硝子
Mr. Oba, you can hang up now.
大庭先生 现在可以挂掉电话了
Okay.
好
What's this about?
这是怎么一回事？
Please give us a moment.
请等一下
Mr. Sawamura, this way please.
泽村先生 这边请
Hey, what are you doing?
你们到底要做什么？
This is not an unlawful possession. It's a test drive.
这不是违法占有 而是试车
-What? -Ishiko, put him in the car.
-什么？ -石子小姐 请他上车
Hey, stop.
给我停车
-Where are you going? -Wait a minute.
-你们要去哪里？ -等一下
-Kawai, get us a car! -Yes, sir.
-川合 快去开车 -是
Hey, what are you doing?
你们要做什么？
Mr. Sawamura.
泽村先生
I'm guessing the branch manager told you that if you helped him frame Mr. Oba,
我想分店长跟你说了 只要你协助陷害大庭先生
he would stop being so strict with you.
他就不会再对你这么严厉
And you ended up participating in his plan.
所以你才会加入他今天的计划
Excuse me, could you fill me in?
等一下 请把来龙去脉说清楚
Mr. Oba had already noticed.
大庭先生早就发现了
That you had betrayed him.
是你背叛了他
I…
我…
Last night, I heard the truth about those messages.
昨晚我问出 那些职权骚扰信息的真相了
I…
我…
I didn't send all of them.
不是全部都我发的
He did send messages to rush him, such as "Hello?"
他的确发了“喂” 这种像是施压的信息
But he didn't send the abusive messages that caused his transfer.
但是造成他调职的霸凌信息 不是他发的
That message was sent
那些信息的发送时间
during the lunch break on my workday.
是在我上班日的午休时间
The branch manager called me in when I was taking a break.
分店长在我休息的时候叫我进去
It was during that time frame.
就是在我回来之前的那个空档
Oba!
大庭
Yes, sir!
是
If you touch the laptop I left behind before it turns to the lock screen,
我的笔记本就这样放着 持续碰它就不会变成锁定画面
anyone can send messages as me even if they don't know my password.
这样即使不知道密码 也可以用我的身份发送信息
The only person who could've done that back then
能这样做的人就只有那时候
was Sawamura, who was with me.
唯一在现场的泽村而已
But even so, Mr. Oba didn't go after you.
即使如此 大庭先生也没有追究你的责任
He went through with it under such obvious circumstances,
那种情况马上就会被发现 但他还是那样做了
so I knew that the branch manager had forced him to do it.
我就知道是分店长强迫他动手的
Hey, stop the car!
快点停车
You felt guilty towards Mr. Oba.
你是因为对大庭先生有愧疚感
Th-That's why you seemed scared of him, right?
才会看起来很怕他的样子 不是吗？
How much of this is going according to plan?
到目前为止 有多少事情是按照你的计划走的
I didn't expect you to tag along.
我没有想到你会跟过来
Other than that, mostly…
除此之外大都是…
Stop the car!
停车
Oh…
哦
Oba!
大庭
You!
我说你啊
-Oba! -Hey, Oba! Wait!
-大庭 -大庭 等一下
Wait!
给我站住
Do you have any idea what you've done?
你知道自己干了什么好事吗？
Last night, I wondered if you'd really call back
昨晚我就在怀疑 再怎么人手短缺
someone you personally transferred, no matter how short-staffed you are.
真的会有人 把调走的员工再叫回来吗？
And so, I came to the conclusion that
因此我得出结论
you've noticed we're up to something and decided to make a move.
你注意到了我们的意图 决定要先下手为强
-What are you talking about? -So we played along to get proof.
-你在说什么？ -所以我决定将计就计 以取得证据
Then why didn't you tell me?
这样为什么不先跟我说？
Because you're very hard-headed.
因为你就是木鱼脑袋
You'd tell me that this plan is a fraudulent act, right?
这样将计就计 你一定会说是欺诈行为吧？
-What's this ab… -Mr. Sawamura.
-等一下 在说什么… -泽村先生
Hey.
等一下
Once you submit the evidence, everything will be over.
只要你提出证据 一切就会结束了
In Mr. Oba's recordings,
在大庭先生拍到的画面里
there was a moment when you seemed to be checking a voice recorder.
有一瞬间你好像在检查录音笔
You're collecting evidence, aren't you?
你一直在搜集证据吧？
Didn't you also record the conversation about today's data tampering?
今天有关篡改资料的对话 你不是也有录下来吗？
Let me hear…
那个录音…
that audio.
请让我听听看
What's this about, Sawamura?!
这是怎么回事 泽村？
Come on!
快啊
Huh?
怎么会？
No?
行不通吗？
Sawamura, come over here.
泽村 过来这里
Please wait.
请等一下
-Hey, let me go! -Hang on!
-请等一下
-Let go! -Sawamura!
-放手 -泽村
What's wrong with you? Let me go!
你干什么 放开我
Sawamura!
泽村
Both of you, calm down.
你们俩冷静点
-Everyone! -Please hang on.
-各位 -请等一下
Everyone!
各位
Why didn't you speak up?
你们为什么都不出声呢？
Mr. Oba. When they covered up the workplace bullying that you reported,
大庭先生 当你告发职场霸凌而被压下来
why didn't you talk to a lawyer right away?
为什么不立刻找律师咨询呢？
Before you started recording from the café.
在你开始去咖啡厅录像之前
Because…
那是因为…
Suing a company I work for
要控告自己任职的公司
felt bad.
还是会畏首畏尾
And it's a private matter,
而且这是公司内部的事情
so depending on someone felt wrong.
要依赖别人还是感觉不太对
Also…
还有…
You felt pathetic.
你觉得很丢脸
But that's not true.
不是这样的
Rules that exist to make human relationships easier.
为了让人际关系更圆满而存在的规则
That is the law.
这才是法律的本质
Speaking up in accordance with those rules is not pathetic nor wrong at all.
根据这些规则发声一点也不丢脸 更没有什么不对
Article 14 of the Constitution
宪法第14条
stipulates that all citizens are equal before the law.
规定全体国民在法律之前一律平等
If you know the law, there are things you can protect or avoid.
了解法律 就能守护很多事 也能避免很多事
You can also minimize the damage.
也能把伤害降到最低
And we are here to help you with that.
我们的工作就是来协助你们
However, we cannot help you unless you speak up.
只是 如果你们不出声求助 我们就帮不上忙
We hope you'll make good use of the law and live a happy life.
希望你们都能善用法律 过着幸福的日子
That's all.
我说完了
Right?
对吧？
Yes.
对
If you'd submit the evidence--
只要愿意提出证据…
Give this document to Oba.
把这份文件交给大庭
Get him fired.
让他被开除吧
Hey, wait…
你这家伙 等一下…
Hey, stop it. Hey!
搞什么 快住手
I will submit this audio!
我愿意提供这份录音
Branch manager, I will report your action to the company
分店长 我会向总公司报告你的行为
and demand appropriate measures.
并要求适当处分
If you cover it up, I'll take it to the Labor Standards Office.
如果试图掩盖 我也会告到劳动基准局
I promise you!
我向你保证
Don't you dare!
开什么玩笑
You can speak up for yourself too!
你也可以为自己发声
What?
什么？
If your actions were due to pressure from a reckless working environment,
如果是因为公司要求不可能的业绩 你的行为造成的压力所导致
you may be able to hold the company accountable for
是劳动环境造成的结果 你也能以违反安全保障义务
violating their safety obligation.
追究公司的责任
If you were forced to work long hours outside of the Article 36 agreement,
如果公司违反36条协议 强迫你长时间工作的话
they may be violating Article 32, Clause 1 of the Labor Standards Act
也可能违反劳基法第32条第1项 保障劳工休息时间
regarding the maximum working hours per week.
不得要求一周工作超过40个小时
Also, Clause 2. "Employers shall not allow workers to work more than
第2项 “保障劳工每周休息时间
eight hours a day excluding break time, for each day of the week."
其余各日不得工作超过八小时”
And I could help you to…
我可以协助你追究公司责任…
A new law to prevent
新的法律能防止
workplace harassment, such as power harassment and sexual harassment
职权骚扰和性骚扰等 职场上常见的骚扰
was enacted by the Diet today.
今天在国会表决通过
Meaning, all companies and firms
提出职场骚扰的对策
must take measures against power harassment in the workplace.
已经成为不只是中小企业 而是所有企业的责任
-Let's dig in. -It's huge!
-我要开动了 -好大碗
-Excuse me. -Wow.
-不好意思 -哇
Thank you.
谢谢
Really, what's wrong with this town?
这个城镇是有什么毛病？
Binge eating is the selling point of this town.
“爆食”是我们镇上的卖点嘛
Eat as much as you want. It's my treat.
多吃一点 我请客
-You don't have to. -Thank you.
不用了 -谢谢招待
Man, that was a quick response.
你的反应也未免太快了
You're that hungry?
很饿吗？
So, are you really resigning?
你真的要辞职吗？
Yes.
对
I'm going to start something new.
我想要去做一些新的事情
I'll hang out with Sawamura as a friend.
我还是可以跟泽村继续当朋友
Delicious, isn't it?
很好吃吧？
Yes.
对
Yeah?
对吧？
Man, I'm so stuffed.
天啊 我吃撑了
Huh?
什么？
Yes, hello?
喂？
Surprisingly, you don't eat a lot, huh?
真意外你胃口这么小
What?
什么？
You eat too much.
是你太会吃了
Do I?
是吗？
Anyway,
总之
good work today.
今天辛苦了
You, too.
你也是
Sono contento.
“索诺坎藤托”
However, we cannot help you unless you speak up.
只是 如果你们不出声求助 我们就帮不上忙
Actually, I--
其实我…
What did you say?
你说什么？
Nah, it's nothing.
不 没什么
What?
什么？
Bye.
先这样了
Good morning!
早安
Morning.
早
Huh? What's this?
怎么会有这个？
It's a gift from that divorce settlement couple.
上次离婚调解的夫妇送的礼物
When Haneo criticized the wife's actions that day,
那天羽男批评妻子的行为时
our client stood up for her, right?
委托人站出来维护她不是吗？
Apparently, that made him realize that he still cares for her
他因此发现自己还是很在乎她
and they decided to stop the divorce for now.
所以决定暂时不离婚了
That's wonderful.
真是太好了
See? I was right after all.
看吧…我果然是对的
It's a coincidence.
只是刚好而已
You may bow down and apologize.
只要你躬身跟我道歉 我就不跟你计较
Did you memo that too?
这句话你也写成了笔记吗
-Don't talk about my memos. -I'm back!
-不要提笔记的事 -我回来了
I didn't write that.
我才没写笔记勒
Hello.
辛苦了
Oh, thank you.
谢谢你 辛苦了
I'm working part-time here from today. Pleasure to work with you!
我从今天起在这里打工 请各位多关照了
-What?
-什么？ -什么
My son paid for game items without telling me.
我儿子瞒着我在游戏里充钱了
Meaning, he lied that he's an adult.
代表他谎称自己已成年
Leave it to me.
交给我吧
You want to win?
你们想赢吧？
Yes, sir!
是
I wonder if he really said he wants to take the exam.
他真的说过想要考试吗
Do you like Ishiko?
你喜欢石子小姐吗？
This is a criminal case.
这是刑事案件
I need to check something.
我想查一件事
Subtitle translation by: Aya Kudo
字幕翻译：赤焰